so he was uh yeah he was a Jain
philosopher who was espousing the view
that um
um
that material you know that a person has
material form as self or they have
feeling herself or they have the five
Aggregates herself
um
and today
I mean that's quite a prominent view for
example in the advice of adanta
non-dualist kind of Hindu video that um
there's a there's an extra temporal
higher self or Universal Consciousness
and Liberation comes from
like surrendering your the inferior self
or the ego to this higher self
um
and yeah it seems to me that that view
is almost
um a necessary
prerequisite to understanding the
Buddhist teaching in the sense that
um yeah in a sense you're trying to find
a way out oh yeah there is you're seeing
this negative
um self-periperal to experience you have
to see that itself to then discern the
nature of that self too you don't see
the impermanence of it or um not not
necessarily like you wouldn't
you would not you could arrive very
differently though you could just arrive
through wanted to be free from suffering
and so on
but yeah say somebody does
have that view have that experience of a
higher self
I have form of self that seems to be
unchanged by these more kind of
perturbing changes that happen on the
level of this kind of temporal self Here
and Now
so you can't just stop having that view
I mean why would you
um
but how can you how can you overcome
that view
so how can you become view of a higher
self that does factually
help you cope with life much better
um helps you uh not be perturbed as much
when this this kind of lower self gets
affected this higher self gives me
perspective so um
so um
well let's say first though what's the
problem what's the problem with that why
is that a problem
why is the advice of you a problem
it's turning Consciousness into a thing
um well I don't know anything about it I
don't know if I never heard the word
Consciousness I don't know anything I
just know that having a high sense of
self makes my life better what's the
problem with it
practically speaking is there an issue
with that why is it an issue to have a
higher self as a reference point
well I I mean yeah I mean ultimate is
because you can't descend with this this
is
yeah yeah I don't need to because I'm
again higher sense yourself frees me
from suffering here and now yeah I don't
need I don't know what you're talking
about this that but this
factually when I'm devoted to the higher
Atman or something I have no pain
what's problem I'm free from something
isn't that what you isn't that what the
Buddhist teaches freedom from suffering
I can bear a lot more I cannot lose
perspective I can maintain my kindness
in regard to others what's the problem
with the higher reference point of a
higher self
my station is there an issue
well it is intoxicating it is very
pleasurable you would see why that is
very difficult to overcome that but why
would you overcome it if it's not enough
I mean you wouldn't I mean that's that's
why people don't right so then are you
saying there is no issue with it I mean
or there is an issue with it yeah that
was yeah like from a personal point of
view yeah am I at risk if I take that
high self am I exposing myself yes of
course because you can't discern the
unknown ability of the self uh so then
unability of it is the problem that's
the issue yeah yeah the lack of
discernment of of the unearnability
um because the uninability is factional
I'm just I'm just I'm just asking about
the the actual
um
property say of that experience yeah
whether you discern it or not sure
that's again from the Buddhist point of
view but imagine somebody a non-bodist
person what is an issue is there an
issue with a higher sense of self
without referring to where Buddhist
teaching is better and three different
things well I'm free from suffering when
I believe when I'm merged with my
ottoman or something so from that point
of view whatever you're saying it's
already what I'm doing
but then is it so
or it isn't is there an issue that that
the whoever partakes in the view is not
aware of is there an issue that whoever
protects in the view is there turning
the Blind Eye towards they're not seeing
it they're ignoring it so yes
honorability of it is an issue
like see you just assume it is your
higher self
but do you know that that higher self is
do you know that that higher self is
also not subjected to the same
perturbing things sure it's on a higher
level so it does not get perturbed as
easily as these other things but
ultimately are you sure that it cannot
be perturbed are you sure that it cannot
turn against you
are you sure that he cannot let you down
are you sure it will obey your will and
save you
how do you know that forever
exactly exactly boils down to that
that's why when he described in the
suitors the practices of other schools
and teachings says yes some salmon and
brahmas with factually establish their
mind upon the great element of Earth and
they would abandon everything inferior
to it but they would not understand the
danger of that element of the word that they
of that element of the word that they
have used to abandon everything in field
the target understands that as well they
will not understand the danger
gratification but facing the engine in
the escape in regard to earth water fire
Atman Consciousness
like the whole seeing brahmas and
everything but conceiving them as yours
and that's the root of the problem it's
not that this sense of self is perturbed
and you need to find a bigger one the
reason whatever you find you're going to
conceive it as yours so that is the the
heart of the issue it's it's even even
the most refined advice experience
fundamentally it's unable it's not yours
that's there is no merging of yourself
it's just basically refining the
experience of exactly what such cassette
of the five aggregates
and that's that's you know in those
other suitors when they would have said
it doesn't matter
if somebody claims I'll show you the all
apart from this all here the five
Aggregates six senses there is no such
thing he's contradicting himself because
there is nothing that he can show you
that's outside of this
so
no matter how far you think you go in
your merging with your higher self and
it's frees you from suffering and makes
you forget about the Troubles of this
life that's still within this life that's
that's still within this life that's
still Within These Aggregates that's
still subjected to these things
and the issue then is when that thing
which is subject to change that higher
self whatever phenomenon you take is
higher self
not seeing that as dependent upon
a lower self well yes yeah that's like
if you want to escape it but the real
issue is simply you're not really
addressing an issue
that's the problem you just replace one
ownership for the other ownership both
things because you conceive them as your
as as ownable that's why they're a
problem see the problem of the inferior
self was not that he was perturbed the
problem was that it was yours while he
was perturbed
so then you realize perturbance cannot
be stopped but ownership can
so you just slow down the perturbance so
to speak by upgrading your higher sense
of self but fundamentally you're still
doing the same thing yeah still you
still you haven't escaped the problem
because of which you're doing what
you're doing so the danger is still
there that you are you are now taking
something which is something to change
as yourself yeah so yeah you're
obviously subject to and you you might
uh be quite comfortable in that
taking that higher self as yourself
which seems permanent so on but at the
end of the day End Of The Line it's
gonna get chicken we will come home you
can get slapped in the face with reality
and how's that going to feel when you
thought you had to escape something that
was permanent and brings you brought you
safety but now it's not why have you
forsaken me Lord yeah yeah exactly yeah
as Jesus said so now say somebody does
recognize okay
so this High Center self
I couldn't get regard it is not mine
equally in the same sense I want to get
rid of overcome this perturbing self
sense of self that's constantly
perturbed I could now have the same attitude
I could now have the same attitude
towards this higher sense of self
so how would they practically
what would they need to do
say somebody does still have a view of
the higher self
you can't just stop thinking it stop
having it how'd you free yourself from
it
so while it's enduring it's a not trying
to get rid of it but see it as
determined by
that which is out of one's control as
the Buddha says in the suit
do you have control like a king has
control over his kingdom so basically
this is you have control over matter
start feeling yeah yeah so start
pondering on its properties
of like well the other saying it's
arising how it rises could you prevent
it from leaving do you know
fundamentally I think the most practical
thing would just come down to
stop regarding it as your friend
because that's a completely gratuitous
attitude that you just took there's
nothing that justified it
but automatically people when they find
a higher self it automatically regarded
as pleasurable mind it's my friend it's
for my welfare it's for my being but if
you stop and think about it there is no
justification for that attitude except
you're taking it for granted as such
it's like why do you think it's your
friend well I guess it makes sense in
the sense that it's uh
impermanence is like
it's less in the sense that it changes
at a slower rate yeah
we don't need to figure out why he took
it as friend and you want to know why
you're still holding you this friend
that's that's what I meant to ask right
no so whichever way one way or the other
you're gonna arrive it
such experience of high self or
meditation experience or peace or
whatever and you're going to regard it
as as friendly as yours as for you as
beneficial as wholesome why is that yeah
why I mean why do you why why do you
just not question that yeah
um so you have the sense of higher self
you don't need to get rid of it you
don't need to psychologize it you don't
need to explain how it came to be you
could just
see it for what it is fully take it
don't deny it and then start regarding
it as but this is not my friend this is
not mine this is not for me this is not
for my welfare
this is dangerous this is a basically
like that suit that says you know a
friend somebody who pretends to be a friend
somebody who pretends to be a friend
just so it can kill you when you turn
away you could choose to regarded that way
you could choose to regarded that way
but that's the more unpleasant
so unless you have a good reason to do
so you naturally won't do so you would
naturally just carry on regarding it as
a friend why because that feels more
pleasant so fundamentally
so fundamentally
chasing pleasure avoiding pain the
reasons that your inferior self has been
perturbed throughout this life
that principle hasn't changed you're
still chasing pleasure avoiding pay just
on a slow but higher rate but still
doing the same thing the same attitude
and that's why the same owner's
Assumption of ownership taking for
granted and everything else so you
haven't that's the problem of the higher
self it's not an escape
it's just another form of pleasure it's
a perpetuation of the same principle
yeah it takes here
it takes here
so yeah have any mystical experience you
want any meditation release you want and then
any meditation release you want and then
regarded as an enemy as a friend as an
enemy who pretends to be a friend who
wants to kill you if you if you kind of
you know turn away from it and cultivate
that attitude and you will put any
passion in regards to the world and your
meditation and Atman and everything else
and you'll be truly free you would
understand gratification
Delight in it the danger oh the Peril
the Trap and then the Escape removal of
the gratification desire towards it in
regard to the loftiest of the mystical
experience that made you feel so special
before and you'll be truly free imperturbable
and you'll be truly free imperturbable
because nothing can be taken as mine now
and that's giving up everything
basically not taking anything as your
not taking anything as your
self
giving up ownership of any on any level
yeah and first you gotta you gotta see
where the problem is in the ownership
without seeing it
you're just going to be taking one thing
instead of the other
so that's that this is the interest pass
okay no whatever
whatever safety I've known found again
if you reflect upon it you realize that
you have no say in it thus you should
not I mean you still can take it as your
safety you still can remain
regarding it as friendly for me Pleasant
for my welfare
but if you're honest you realize well
I'm I don't know
I don't know
that that's that is factually so
logistics thing is factually friendly
yet I just choose to regard it because
alternative feels more unpleasant so
that's all I'm doing is acting
away from Pain towards pleasure like
what always have been doing so oh that's
why I'm unsafe so then a man truly won't
think he's on welfare will realize no I
must abandon that
that ownership that craving in regard to
feeling and then then I'll deal with what's
and then then I'll deal with what's
there left I don't know what's going to
be don't matter but I know that this
problem won't be there
so you're not concerned then what's
going to happen after you're just
concerned removing what's here and now
that is an issue and the base for
suffering
and it is here and now you know that's
what would have said that's another
famous passage that often gets mystified
like in this with this oh no stop you
know stop kind of going over the past
and like oh about where you will be and
what will be in the future
here what's present that's what you
should abandon
even now that's what I'm abandoning as
in that's the root of the problem I have
refrained from yeah
or also at the same time I have
refrained from well in the past I did
this who did it no no here and now is
the issue in regards to craving in
regard to feeling in regard to ownership
assumption and that is what I'm
abandoning and then past and future
believing themselves out
but that that as I said that gets
mystified like I don't think about the
past don't plan the future just be here
now well no
just abandon your being here and now
understand it discern it
relinquish it regard it as an enemy not
be here now wow look at this Universal
Joy of this this moment-to-moment
experience no sure whatever you describe it
no sure whatever you describe it
the pure Consciousness my enemy
but it's infinite awareness I'm a threat
pedal Here and Now brought the experience of
Here and Now brought the experience of
this present moment
a trap
yeah there's no there's no reason to be
here now and regard it as a trap every
single second of your being there rather
than rather than you did the work
already by being here now that's why I
say all these other teachers and
teachings and Views that kind of they
come up to or be here now that's the
combination you can have different
permutations of where they come from and
what do you do in account what do you do
in order to get there but the
combination is present moment here and
now that's it that's it celebrate that's
it yeah it's like no that's where dumb
actually starts Yeah by all means be
here now and then start doing the work
of abandoning that here and now through
seeing the danger of it the
gratification the pedal
not just mystifying it in in and milking
that experience more and more
but you can't be here now
if you're intoxicated yeah
yeah exactly
but then you also should not have a view
that oh now I'm here and now my work's
done I'm here and now let me find what
work I need to do now yeah
how do I abandon this here right now how
do I prevent the possibility of
intoxication arising in the future by
Discerning how do I uproot my dependence
on the pleasure of Here and Now
how I remove any need for safety in Here
and Now
how I get my mind to turn away from here
and now
yes okay well by contemplating danger in
Here and Now sufficiently
the only way to get
to see here and now
is to not distract yourself
with sensual pleasures
yeah because it says as I said before
like be here and now as opposed to where
where else can you be yes okay I'll stop
thinking about the past why you are
doing that here and now oh don't plan
about a future how's that possible and
why would you not plan about what you're
doing it here and now if I think about
the future I'm doing it presently Here
and Now what do you do I'm thinking I'm
just planning what you can do tomorrow
here and now
so why is that an issue
so you can't live here and now even if
you want to people want to leave here
and now when Here and Now is unpleasant
yes but when Here and Now is Pleasant oh
then they want to mystify it
but it's like but it's still the same
here and now
as a framework of Here and Now
it's it's still there
so why do you want to leave it on some
occasions why do you want to stop
thinking about the past that's done here
and now oh because all this pain is
coming up oh so you just want to be here
and now when it's not unpleasant you're
going to be here and now in order to
avoid the pain oh here and now
so that's why it's not it's never a
resolution it's just perpetuation of the
same issue
so first yeah you gotta recognize that
the only way to be here and now is not
by intending to be here and now
but it's a by by not distracting
yourself from here and now
not forgetting that you cannot not be
here right now
and you will forget that when you engage
with your senses
mystical ideas protruders ownerships and
safeties and so on just if you engage
with craving yeah if you start acting on
a cream because you are by acting out of
craving you're anticipating the future
pleasure So you you're just in this
anticipation isn't it so you're not
hearing now exactly
but you completely but you don't want to
be here right now you want to be
somewhere else here and now later on
when that here and now is Pleasant yeah
so yeah exactly exactly the removal of
craving means like that there is no other option
means like that there is no other option
but to fully be here enough
because you are healing now
it's a bit don't worry abandon the
future don't worry about the future
don't have anticipation remove that yeah
don't Delight in it
they're crazy exactly but you can't like
I mean
From Here and Now moment next Here and
Now moment it's already me thinking
about the future yeah so you cannot
think about the future means like they
would be being unconscious
and same if you can think about a future
means there will be there is an implicit
past carried with it
equally to mean you're unconscious if
you stop thinking about the past
just merge yourself in the present
moment well why do you need to merge
yourself with it when you're already in
it so now that thinks about the future
thinks about the past and but the idea
so they are now here enough so what's
the difference oh the difference is that
that Here and Now feels unpleasant
so basically I don't really care about
here and now or Atman for that matter
anything else I just care about not
feeling this this comfort and pain
so how they deal with it by replacing
with pleasure an ignorant way if a
person starts to even though it doesn't
matter even if you're engaging in that
but you actually start honestly asking
yourself certain questions and you
recognize that okay but the principle is
still the same
here I am claiming Here and Now is the
way out while here and now I'm trying to
get rid of the here and now that's not
on my own terms yeah
so here and now then it's not the way
out and it's not really even about here
and now or here and there or whatever
else it's about me getting rid of the
pain when I'm touched by it and me
having pleasure or prolonging it when
I'm touchpad so that's the route to the
problem that's the root of the unsafety
so how about
stop worrying about yeah stop worrying
about past the future or here and now
for that matter
undo your attitude
towards pleasure and your attitude
towards pain and your attitude towards
neutral feeling that's all you need to
do
so how do I start that what do I do well
come here Monk dwell restrained by the
precepts that's how you start
and it will make sense if if you want to
approve the craving in regard to your
feeling like if I feel Pleasant you want
to remove the desire for more if you
feel uncomfortable you want to remove
that diversion they're trying to get rid
of it and if you feel neutral you want
to remove that just distracted indolence
of forgetting about yourself and
drifting away
so first thing you do well okay well you
gotta you gotta restrain your behavior
by Body you can't be engaging with these
things that already depend on this
craving in regard to your feeling while
expecting to remove the craving in
regard to your feeling so well
restrained by the rules of patimoka so
to say then God descends those then be
moderate in eating basically tone down
tame it contain the behavior don't let
it keep spilling out on on a various
basis of craving
and then the mind and the here and now
and everything else can become apparent
and then you could also exercise then
these attitudes towards it okay so this
is perilous this is not to be welcome
this is not to be delighted in I don't
need to get rid of it I can't get rid of
getting rid of it would be another form
of a version of it so again I'm back
onto craving
so then you teach your mind how to
remain calm in regard to pleasure in
regard to pain in regarding you to
feeling calm by that I don't mean
focused on your nostrils unaware of
what's happening I mean unmoved by it
so when pleasure touches you he knows it
he sees it he doesn't leap at it when
pain touches he doesn't shrivel away
from it have a neutral feeling touches
it touches that that dead mind it does
not drift away and just unaware of it
so yeah in other way he he knows
he he knows his suffering
he he can be with his suffering it's
like all the preception is helping you
to be with the suffering you have to
stop trying to get rid of it on impulse
which is the reason for your suffering
in the first place the impulse or
craving yeah initially I guess you have
to take this on faith in in a sense like
um the more you well relatively speaking
yeah sure there's still there's some
logic to it yeah exactly that's what I
mean it's not on the fair okay I'll just
have I have no discernment at all I'll
just believe in this yeah yeah you have
to take it on faith because the result
of correct application of medicine you
know will have to follow later on you're
not immediately gonna see the skin cream
working but if you have faith to apply
it I'm on account of you know some
discernment you will find out that it's
working exactly so so but in this case I
say oh it's yes it is a degree of Faith
but not like like absolute kind of
irrational blind fate because as I said
if you already recognize
you know the desire the suffering the
pressure of sensuality the pressure of
suffering the pressure of aversion the
pressure of hindrances there's a that's
the real problem here is this craving
desire that kind of the impulse that
controls me that overwhelms me that I
then act out of
while at the same time I don't want to I
would like to not I mean the only reason
you act out of this desires is because
you want to be free from them when they
touch you so if you already start
recognizing that you realize that if you
then somebody comes yeah well I have a
way out but you got to be sense
restrained you won't be far-fetched it
won't be like poor where did that come
from now
that makes sense it makes sense you're
just oh yeah come on like I have to I oh
here I'm practicing I'm I'm unmovable
samadhi like being being sort of fully
sort of imperturbable while you know
side sounds math test touches I'm still
chasing like a rabid animal
so I I have to I have to contain that if
you start doing it sure then later in
further understanding you gotta have
some faith in and stick to it and keep
doing it and keep practicing the
Restraint of precepts until other things
become more self-evident in which case
now you see a direct relationship
between The Taming of the mind and the
results of freedom from suffering
then you see the danger very clearly and
it's like yeah yeah then you don't need
any more faith nor convincing no
reminders to stick with it the cream is
working it's working and you're
realizing what everything else you see
somebody without a cream basically how
how aggravated the condition is now and
so I I dodged that bullet I avoid that
if you and so if you don't if you're
unable to have pause
not just reacting going after trying to
uh appease your pain and go after
pleasure if you don't have that any
restraint you will not be able to
you will not be able to
sit with your suffering
sit with the craving and see it as
dangerous and therefore your mind turn
away from their craving and most
importantly you won't be able to to
recognize the neutral feeling
because if if there is neither pleasure
or pain that would be very painful
there will be the the dread the anxiety
the the madness you will be losing your
mind that's why if if a neutral feeling is
that's why if if a neutral feeling is
not known not understood not discerned
it's unpleasant as I said to say
if neutral feeling is understood and
discerned it's Pleasant
and that is that is what that's why
people would
even prefer engagement with pain
anything but being bored left alone sort
of Mind drifting away from itself in
solitude without any distractions that's
the the worst thing a person can imagine
anything else exactly it feels like
dying because it is a form of dying
everything else as long as there isn't
something to to fight for or overcome
defend well it's still exactly brings
hope brings this brings all these sort
of uh active active forms of Engagement
that that keep you for what you are
there he is the only way to see the
dukkah in feelings is to not act out of
it because then you get to experience
the the feeling the pressure of it yeah
the extent of it and say well you get no
matter what I do about it that basis of
pressuring feeling remains yeah without
Delight in it hated try to fight it
ignore it whatever yeah
the basis remains
it's like well I might as well just
okay I'll leave it now I'm leaving it
I'm leaving it
I'm leaving it have a left I'm leaving
it even that can become something to do
a person would do so you have to
recognize yeah inevitably your efforts
will not be correct but they will be not
as wrong seriously at least if you're
now Discerning and knowing the view that
you should really not have to do
anything on account of anything that's
being felt and that can only be done if
you have endured Kanti patiently uh
sort of been under a pressuring feeling
without acting out without trying to get
rid of it without turning a blind eye to
it
and that's how the mind is forced
basically to grow
grow away from it it so it turns away
you don't turn it away yeah it turns
Away by default by C by what you doing
is basically keeping the clarity yeah
not covering up what's right in front of
you to see it for what it is see the see the
to see it for what it is see the see the
nature of it for what it is impermanent
suffering and the mind will be turning
away but the problem is that you don't want
but the problem is that you don't want
to Bear the pain of seeing the
impermanence it's uncomfortable that's
sitting there not doing anything about
it it is difficult to see like the queen
I mean and that's why sense restrained
virtue is so integral to this yeah
the same cream is not difficult you see
craving is is impossible because you
don't want to do the other difficult
work which is not act out of your
feelings
those watchfulness Solitude that's the
difficult part if you actually cultivate
that diligently you will see the craving
it's it cannot not be seen it's not like
and then I need to make where do I look
for it no no it's going to be right
there but you have to be
um like uncompromising in the standard
of like Solitude yeah yeah that is
difficult because well you have to be
uncompromising in not acting out of your
craving and authentic awesome not acting
out of greed not acting aversion not
actual distraction that's what you need
to be on compromisable so you can think
keep the precepts God descends those
watchfulness of your intentions there's
no compromise there
and then it's easy and then Solitude
will come you don't even have because
sometimes people can jump at the idea of
solitude because like the idea of not
being bothered but you're already
bothered um so don't worry about a solitude part
um so don't worry about a solitude part
precepts guarding of the centers
watchfulness of your intentions
and that will factually result
in samadhi in mind turning away in being
more composed less perturbable and
craving more obvious that's and then
yeah Solitude will be the natural result
of that as well
but yeah it means that means like okay I
am guarding these sense those and
practicing and keeping the precepts
because I want to contain the mind until
the craving becomes apparent so I'm free
from it not because oh you know they
said why mustn't do this
um my tradition
declares I should keep these rules thus
I'm doing it on the paper no no you do
it because you want to every single time
so you need to feel that responsibility
and option of not doing it at any single
time and that's the unpleasant part
initially until you get used to it
right so you need to feel that edge
don't compromise there and then yeah
do not seek unsuitable site sounds
maltase touches
how do you know what's in suitable
because the letter
Define it or the rule didn't Define it
does it mean suitable or no
although even the rule doesn't mention
it
the precepts don't mention that I
shouldn't look at this I won't look at
it because it's rooted I know for fact
it's rooted in in desire oh there's
nothing wrong with it there is
everything wrong with it because it's
rooted in your desire that's what's
wrong with it
but if you still judge things on account
of the sense objects
the external Authority you're not seeing
your intentions which means you're not
doing what I said should be done
watchfulness of your intentions it's not
being done guarding of the sense those
is not being done precepts are not being
done even while you're keeping them
because you're keeping them on that
external level to your craving is
maintained wow wow slightly more
constricted yeah yeah you created a new
environment around it but see now you
start having all these views on account
of it they're the fully justifying uh
you're craving and your behavior and not
approving anything that's what Buddha
said when someone was environments do
start dwelling kind of become restrained
withdrawn from sensuality then they fall
into all these like views and holding
these views and arguing overviews and
sort of fighting overview like views
become your thing
that that self-righteousness
justification I deal with our Pure and
all judged by these external criteria
they have nothing to do with right or
wrong greediversion delusion non-greed
greediversion delusion non-greed
non-version non-delusion that's right or
wrong that's it
and then as I said craving will have to
be seen show itself
so I'm about to do something
he's against precepts no okay
is it routine design is it routinely
well is it rooting irritation is it
rooted in cruelty is it rooted in
distraction easy rooted in carelessness
yeah okay I should not do it then
but the precept is fine yeah
by the guarding of the senzo says it's
not fine
but the watchfulness of your intention
says it's not fine so you have a view
now you have a choice to make
are you gonna take the responsibility
and use this internal criteria of great
diversion delusion non-gritty
non-version illusion for the base
whether you should act or not or you're
gonna go well
I can do it if it's fine for him it's
fine for me
and that's it yeah that person means
you're not taking it internally you're
not you have not taken him in the
precepts rightly
yeah it's the pull to do to continue
acting is there and there is still um
yeah this pressure and then then you
know the choice to not act is as well
yeah that's where the work is which
allows you to then discern craving which
allows you to then yeah that would say
like it's not you know uh understanding
the Dharma seeing the craving it's not
like as I said it's this hidden Mystery
and secret that you kind of have to like
really really discern and work hard
intellectually to get to
no you have to work hard to withdraw
yourself from where you are
you draw the Mind from the senses from
the dependence on the pleasure of the
senses from acting out of pressure and
then you'll see it it's right there it's
gonna be right there in your face very
tangible yeah yeah so that's the the
difficult part is exactly what nobody
wants to do
you know people can sit for hours in
ponderendama and figure it out and read
the dictionaries and get the degrees in
it and know every single text and loads
of effort I mean factually loads of
effort and time and discomfort
but but they don't want to do he's in
due to pressure on the level of feeling
and not take tired of it not get rid of
it not try to justify it not to
psychologize it not explain it
just endure it
endure it
without distracting yourself from it
without falling back onto the senses to
cover it up
that's the
that's the middle way yeah that's why
it's not done
because it's the softest one to see and
stick with it
but if somebody is diligent in that
regarding yeah
you don't even have to worry about
craving it but it's so bad and
everything else
it's just going to be seen there
very real very yeah and also where it is
okay you see when you're trying to think
about it before you have developed
your behavior your mind withdrawn from
centrality that which you think craving is isn't
that which you think craving is isn't
that which you think your Aggregates are
art it's misconceived
it's misconceived
whatever he conceives it's always
different than that as I said it says
because of your conceiving